<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-24T20:22:24-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Annabel Rothschild</title><entry><title type="html">PhD Recruiting Panel Discussion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/PhD-Recruiting-Talk.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PhD Recruiting Panel Discussion" /><published>2020-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/PhD-Recruiting-Talk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/PhD-Recruiting-Talk.html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the larger “PhD Recruiting” event, I’m speaking on a panel with some other super cool folks about the PhD experience and how we arrived at our current positions. The whole event is geared towards students both interested in a PhD and those who aren’t sure if it’s the right choice for them, so join us! More information, &lt;a href=&quot;https://phd-recruiting.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ps. If you didn’t find out about the event in time to sign up, there are still ways for you to get involved with the community at the above link.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Annabel</name></author><summary type="html">As part of the larger “PhD Recruiting” event, I’m speaking on a panel with some other super cool folks about the PhD experience and how we arrived at our current positions. The whole event is geared towards students both interested in a PhD and those who aren’t sure if it’s the right choice for them, so join us! More information, here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Meta thoughts on grad school apps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/Grad-School-Application-Thoughts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meta thoughts on grad school apps" /><published>2020-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-07-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/Grad-School-Application-Thoughts</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/07/11/Grad-School-Application-Thoughts.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post, and everything else I write about meta-CS is subject to this &lt;a href=&quot;/../meta/grain-of-salt.html&quot;&gt;take with a grain of salt policy&lt;/a&gt;. I strongly encourage you to read it and also note that I reiterate advice a lot of great people have shared with me, and am not myself the orb of all practical knowledge (not that you thought I was, but just in case you were being nice, in which case, thanks!).&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was searching for advice on applying to PhD programs, I was intimidated by how straightforward everyone else’s journeys seemed to be: they went to college, they got involved in research and had a lightning bolt moment, their CVs magically exploded with top tier publications/research internships/etc, and then they became superstar PhD students and eventually professors (with a lot of work along the way, of course). It seemed like they had never had to start out, they just &lt;em&gt;became&lt;/em&gt; amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, as I write this now (a full year after starting the application process), I just had a conversation with a prospective PhD student who was like, “you went straight from undergrad! You’re so together!” and I cackled uncontrollably for a minute, because the latter statement is a lie. We then had a great conversation about overcoming self doubt, which inspired me to write this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back, I suspect it was more so the case that many of the folks whose materials I was reading were merely giving useful, factual tips about applying to graduate programs and didn’t have time for long-winded narratives (like that I’m writing) all of which is very justified and makes a lot of sense. However, it also scared the s*** out of me and led me to think that they had been preordained in some way I hadn’t been and that this wasn’t a space I should be trying to enter. (An important note: I really don’t think anyone tried to give off this tone – certainly, no one was attempting any gate keeping shenanigans considering they put this information out to literally encourage and help other potential applicants – and I was extra sensitive reading it.) In talking to a few folks in person, however, I got a much wider idea of what those pre-PhD experiences might look like, something I found incredibly helpful and made the whole application (and idea of graduate school) seem much more accessible, given that it was all quite new to me. I’m trying to share my somewhat-curvy path here in order to give another story for your consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I went to college, I worked for a summer at a traditional corporate American company. There was absolutely nothing wrong with the company, and it was an excellent first job in which I learned a lot of very practical skills. I realized, though, that I tend to work in shorter, intense spurts (as opposed to a 9-5 position) and I like doing a variety of things over the course of a work day, as opposed to having one role and working on fairly similar projects that fell into that role’s domain. Looking back, those were probably good indicators that I might like the less-predictable nature of research, but I certainly didn’t have that revelation at the time. To be clear, the most I knew about a PhD at that point was that it was an advanced degree involving the title “doctor” (fancy!) and I thought it probably cost money (in reality for CS every position I’ve seen technically pays you, in that it gives you a living stipend and waives tuition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from a brief experience with computer science in high school about which we need not speak more, I went off to college prepared to be an English major and have nothing to do with CS. I switched to CS at the end of my first year, however, mostly because I liked the informal air of the department, there were some scheduling conflicts with the other courses I planned on taking, and I was concerned about having an employable major (note: there is plenty of evidence that shows that English majors are indeed employable and that they make excellent critical thinkers, etc, but I didn’t know that at the time. English majors are great and this is not a post about ‘don’t be an English major’ at all, it’s just what I was thinking at the time). So the summer after my first year I taught CS because it was something related to my major, I hadn’t really tried teaching before and thought I might like it, and also I needed to get a summer job and it paid. Again, fairly practical considerations here, nothing too romantic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent my sophomore year being pretty unsure of what it was I wanted to do, joining a research lab because I liked that it tied CS and current events together (and I liked working with data, too, I found out after taking a class with the lab’s PI, the excellent Prof. Eni Mustafaraj). That summer I participated in an REU program, working with Prof. Yanni Loukisassas, which proved to be a great intro into what full-time (or a more traditional research career) could look like. Despite plenty of challenging moments, I realized it’s very fun to learn things on the fly. By my third year of college, I was somewhat blowing off coursework to focus on various projects (I do not advise this and it was a stressful time, also compounded by other issues). That summer I worked on a project outside of my comfort zone with Prof. Dr. Torben Wallbaum, which definitely solidified my research interests and gave me perspective on the field more generally. I came back for my last year of college and worked on a thesis with Prof. Ada Lerner, mostly because I preferred research to coursework, and Ada very generously let me try a variety of fields out and combine it into one piece of work, as a final round of confirming my research interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concurrently, I’d been teaching CS in various forms (since the summer after my first year of college) and knew that I liked doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I effectively decided in August (immediately prior to the start of my senior year) that I wanted to apply for graduate programs (with applications due in December, and a second round in May/June), though I’d been considering it for maybe three or four months prior as well. For a long time, I was quite sure I was going to do my Masters (MSc) degree in Germany right after my undergrad, which played a big role in many of the choices I made – for example, going the formal thesis route vs an independent study because I thought it would help translate the content of a liberal arts degree – but then a few things happened after I submitted my applications in December that made staying in the United States a much better option for the time being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In actually doing the paperwork for my applications, I had another round of internal struggles related to, “am I cut out for this?” I was scared to reach out to professors I was interested in working with (how was I supposed to reach out to a research icon and question something about their work? Ask them insightful questions? Yeah sure, lemme email someone at the top of the field with 20 years of experience why they chose x methodology, because I’m already an expert on methodologies?), as well as to ask for recommendations from those I had already worked with (which for the record was stupid because there were all really lovely about it and also people secretly sometimes enjoy writing recommendation letters? Incredible.) I thought it was a lot of money just to apply and I was really worried about what was going to happen when I &lt;em&gt;didn’t&lt;/em&gt; get in. Actually, I wasn’t just worried, I was petrified – I spent a good hour with one of our career education advisors plying her with questions like “DO COMPANIES STILL RECRUIT IN FEBRUARY??”. All of this was to say, I did not engage in this process with a very high degree of self-confidence, and while I really don’t think this needs to be the case for anyone (because you’re wonderful! You’re smart! You’re talented!), you shouldn’t be embarrassed if it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never had a thunderbolt moment of “wow! this is the job for me!”, or “I’m destined for a PhD!”. As far as I am aware, I am the first in my extended family to get a PhD, or any graduate degree within my immediate family, meaning that it wasn’t something I expected, or was expected, to do. While I did have friends whose parents were professors growing up, I didn’t really know much about graduate school or consider staying in academia as a career until basically my senior year of college, mainly because I was pretty sure I couldn’t afford it unless I worked for several years post-college. This is in comparison to some of the folks around me who were raised by full-time academics and had a much deeper insight into the process than I did, and a very different perspective on how hard or easy it was to gain entry into these programs. Again, this stressed me out, and I wondered if I really had any business applying until I had more experience or was magically ordained or something. Tapped on the shoulder by the grad schools higher beings (I’m being very dramatic here, yes). [To that end, if you’re new to this PhD business for any reason about would like help applying to graduate school and/or would like a sounding board or essay draft reader, etc, be in touch. Also application fees and GREs are idiotic and exclusionary and we should get rid of them. These are not original thoughts, sure, but just things I think are worth reiterating on literally every platform someone gives me (sorry, also, yes, I gave myself this own platform so unclear if it counts).]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still very privileged though, in approaching this process, in two ways that are important to note:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I was very fortunate in that while I needed to be employed during the school year and the summer, I was able to be employed in ways that (in retrospect) strengthened my CS background and resume – lots of TA-ing, for example. Those jobs (at my undergrad institution) also required more hours and were usually not well-paid (as far as student jobs go), meaning that my last two years of college were effectively really stressful (taking classes, researching in one or more labs, and teaching), so there exist tradeoffs, but I definitely was on the lucky side.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Money played a huge role in my deciding what kind of degree to apply for (I couldn’t have stayed in the US and done my MSc here, for example) and definitely changed the way I went about applying. I spent a lot of time getting assurances that there were still jobs that would be available after (I presumed) I would hear about being rejected and need to find something fast and prepared to spend the majority of January and February job searching (given the Autumn tech recruiting season). BUT, I did know that if I gained acceptance into a program, I needed only to support myself and my health and living conditions would allow me to subsist on a graduate student salary, even though I still complain about it. This last bit is relative to the rather expensive city in which I’m studying, too; I know of folks for whom their graduate stipend was the most secure economic situation they’d ever been in and they were able to save for the first time. I guess my point here is to say that I was lucky my situation was such that I could choose to make a comparatively lower salary than I would have with a regular job.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In closing, I had plenty of reservations about the materials I was submitting, too. My GRE scores were factually strong in writing but very weak in mathematics (below the averages for – I think – every program I applied to that listed their scores, keep in mind I was applying to CS programs). I felt good about my research background, less so about my GPA that showed some spotty experiences with a subject not entirely unrelated to CS. I hadn’t ever worked in industry (which, depending on who you talk to, is sometimes a thing people thought I should have had, though I don’t necessarily agree) and I didn’t have a lot of research artifacts beyond one paper at a lovely, though not super competitive venue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I had one particularly useful somewhat-life-changing conversation with a current graduate student, who told me that above all else, she thought there was a good deal of luck involved with the grad school application process. As in, everyone who applies to PhD programs is probably more than qualified, it’s just a question of who has what funding, who’s taking students this year, etc. That conversation definitely solidified my decision to take the risk and apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I had a lot of excellent advice from people much more familiar with higher education than I was (older friends, professors), and clearly came from a privileged background, I was still pretty intimidated about applying for a PhD and getting in successfully. My point in writing this is to say that I am at least one person (and I’m sure there are a lot more, actually I know there are) who weren’t born magical geniuses who always knew a PhD was in their future and went out and got it. I am really happy to talk about bumps in the road or difficult circumstances that surround applying for graduate degrees like those I am working on, whether that’s being a reader for a draft of an essay or giving a pep talk about how you really are a talented candidate! I’m serious! I can make that blanket statement because anyone willing to spend several years of their life under not the most-necessarily-lovely-pay-and-work-conditions is driven by something serious.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Annabel</name></author><summary type="html">This post, and everything else I write about meta-CS is subject to this take with a grain of salt policy. I strongly encourage you to read it and also note that I reiterate advice a lot of great people have shared with me, and am not myself the orb of all practical knowledge (not that you thought I was, but just in case you were being nice, in which case, thanks!).</summary></entry></feed>